<help>

  <name>mri_seg_overlap</name>

  <usage>mri_seg_overlap [options] &lt;vol1&gt; &lt;vol2&gt;</usage>

  <description>
This program computes the structural overlap between two segmentation volumes. The following statistics can be calculated for each label:

      dice coefficient     -  F1-measure of the similarity between
                              the two labels.
      jaccard coefficient  -  Intersecting volume over the combined
                              volume of the two labels.
      volume difference    -  Fractional difference in volumes of
                              the labels.

By default, only dice scores are computed, but this can be reconfigured with the --measures flag.

Each structure in the input volumes will be considered by default, but an alternative list of labels can be specified with the --labels or -labelfile flags. Additionally, the --seg flag will compute the overlap between the following 12 major anatomical structures:

      Cerebral White Matter (2,41)
      Cerebral Cortex (3,42)
      Hippocampus (17,53)
      Caudate (11,50)
      Putamen (12,51)
      Pallidum (13,52)
      Amygdala (18,54)
      Thalamus Proper (10,49)
      Lateral Ventricle (4,43)
      Third and Fourth Ventricles (14,15)
      Inf Lateral Vent (5,44)
      Accumbens Area (26,58)
  </description>

  <arguments>
  <optional>

    <argument>-o, --out [FILE]</argument>
    <explanation>Save detailed overlap report to a JSON file.</explanation>

    <argument>-m, --measures  [MEASURE...]</argument>
    <explanation>List of measures to compute. By default, only dice scores are computed. Options include: dice, jaccard, voldiff</explanation>

    <argument>-l, --labels  [LABEL...]</argument>
    <explanation>Space-separated list of label values to include. By default, the overlap will be computed between all labels available in both input volumes.</explanation>

    <argument>-n, --names  [LABELNAME...]</argument>
    <explanation>Custom label names corresponding to the values specified with the --labels flag.</explanation>

    <argument>-f, --labelfile  [FILE]</argument>
    <explanation>Text file specifying the label values to include. This file must be in the format of a freesurfer lookup-table, in which each line contains a label value and, optionally, a corresponding label name.</explanation>

    <argument>-x, --no-names</argument>
    <explanation>Do not report label names.</explanation>

    <argument>-s, --seg</argument>
    <explanation>Compute overlap between the the major segmentation structures listed above.</explanation>

    <argument>-q, --quiet</argument>
    <explanation>Quiet mode - do not print results to stdout.</explanation>

  </optional>
  </arguments>

</help>
